Guide to the David Newton Henderson Papers, 1930-1976 RL.00528
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
David Newton Henderson papers
1930-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Henderson, David Newton, 1921-
RL.00528
218 Linear Feet
Correspondence, reports, speeches, drafts of bills, notes, newsletters, printed material, clippings, and other papers, relating to Henderson's service as representative from the 3rd Congressional district of North Carolina, including material relating to his work on the Post Office, Civil Service, and Public Works committees, and to civil rights, minimum wage, federal aid to education, the Vietnam Conflict, anti-poverty programs, foreign aid, tobacco, Watergate, the energy crisis of the early 1970s, and local affairs and projects in eastern North Carolina.
439 Boxes
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Henderson Papers were presented to Duke University by Congressman Henderson upon his retirement from Congress in 1976.
Notes on Processing and Arrangement
The arrangement of this collection has generally followed the system of organization used by Henderson's office. For Federal and State Agencies, Subject Files, and Committee Files, Henderson's staff started a new file each year. In each case these yearly files were consolidated into a comprehensive alphabetical file for the whole period, 1961-1976. Folder headings were left as they were given by Henderson's office except when clarification or more detail was necessary.
Certain material in the original collection was discarded such as routine requests for publications, general information, autographs, pictures, flags, tickets to the White House, etc. Samples of orchestrated pressure mail and Henderson's responses were retained along with a count of the letters received, but repetitive copies were discarded. Case Files only for the letter C were retained. In the Military Academy Files, confidential files for individual applicants and appointees were destroyed. For the Post Office Files, samples were retained only for county seats and Morehead City.
Photographs are scattered throughout the papers. Many are located in the Subject Files under the heading Photographs. Most of these are undated and were left in order as Henderson arranged them. They roughly correspond to years.
When papers were in fairly good order, non-dated Items have been left in sequence where they appeared. In some instances where papers were so disarranged that sequence gave no clue to the dates of such Items, they were placed at the beginning of the folder.
Dates on the folder headings indicate the period of the working papers, but these papers might contain printed material written at an earlier date. Dated printed material was left with the papers in the context in which it was used. This material is often background information, copies of older bills, laws, and regulations.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1921 Born, April 16, on a farm near Hubert, Onslow County, North Carolina.
1942 Graduated with B.S. degree from Davidson College; married Mary Wellons Knowles of Wallace, North Carolina, December 11; their three sons are David Bruce, Wiley Bryant, and Wimbric Boney.
1942-1946 Commissioned as second lieutenant in Army Air Corps, served overseas in India, China, and Okinawa, discharged as major in Air Force.
1949 Graduated with LL.B. from University of North Carolina Law School, Chapel Hill.
1949-1950 Practiced law in Wallace.
1951-1952 Served as Assistant General Counsel to the Committee on Education and Labor, U.S. House of Representatives.
1952-1954 Practiced law in Wallace.
1954-1958 Elected and served as solicitor of the Duplin County General Court.
1958-1960 Elected and served as judge of the same court.
1960-1976 Elected to the 87th Congress as Representative for the Third District of North Carolina, November 8, 1960; served continuously until retirement in 1976.
Committee Assignments
Committee Assignments:
87th Congress 1961-1962
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittees on Census and Government Statistics, Manpower Utilization
88th Congress 1963-1964
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittee on Manpower Utilization (Chairman); Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Public Buildings and Grounds, Rivers and Harbors
89th Congress 1965-1966
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittees on Manpower Utilization (Chairman), Postal Operations; Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Flood Control, Public Buildings and Grounds, Rivers and Harbors, Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Appalachia
90th Congress 1967-1968
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittees on Manpower and Civil Service (Chairman), Position Classification, Retirement Insurance and Health Benefits; Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Flood Control, Public Buildings and Grounds, Rivers and Harbors, Special Subcommittees on Economic Development Programs, Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Appalachia
91st Congress 1969-1970
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittees on Manpower and Civil Service (Chairman), Retirement Insurance and Health Benefits; Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Flood Control, Rivers and Harbors, Roads, Special Subcommittee on Economic Development Programs, Ad Hoc Subcommittee on Appalachia
92nd Congress 1971-1972
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittees on Manpower and Civil Service (Chairman), Postal Facilities; Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Flood Control and Internal Development, Rivers and Harbors, Roads, Special Subcommittee on Economic Development Programs
93rd Congress 1973-1974
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, Subcommittees on Manpower and Civil Service (Chairman), Investigations; Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Water Resources, Transportation, Economic Development, Investigations and Reviews, Energy
94th Congress 1975-1976
Post Office and Civil Service Committee, (Chairman), Subcommittee on Manpower and Civil Service (Chairman); Public Works Committee, Subcommittees on Aviation, Economic Development, Public Buildings and Grounds
Related Material
Graham Arthur Barden Papers, 1934-1960
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Collection Overview
The David Newton Henderson Papers contain the office files of Congressman Henderson when he was the U.S. Representative for the Third District of North Carolina. The papers span from 1930 to 1976, but the bulk of the papers covers Henderson's years in office, 1961-1976. Henderson's predecessor, Congressman Graham A. Barden, left Henderson many papers on ongoing business, especially local projects.
The Henderson Papers contain correspondence, printed material, speeches, invitations, newspaper clippings, photographs, newsletters, financial statements, legislative reports and notes, and drafts of bills. The great majority of this collection is correspondence which Henderson's office exchanged with constituents, legislative officials, and officials of federal and state agencies.
The papers are divided into the following fifteen series:
Campaign Files
Case Files
Committee Files
Correspondence: Answer Copies
County Project Files
Engagements
Federal and State Agencies
Legislation
Military Academy Files
Newsletters and News Releases
Newspaper Clippings
Post Office Files
Speeches
Subject Files
Oversize Box
The largest series are Committee Files, County Project Files, Federal and State Agencies, Legislation, and Subject Files. The Committee Files contain material relating to Henderson's various committee and subcommittee memberships and reflect the actual creation of legislation. The Legislation Series contains drafts of specific bills and legislative reports and notes. Subject Files contain mostly constituent mail on legislation, current issues, and various subjects. County Project Files concern projects and local affairs in the Third District. The Federal and State Agencies Series reflects Henderson's role as an intermediary between constituents' problems and requests and the appropriate governmental agency which could deal with their problems.
There is some overlap among series. For example, using the broad subject Agriculture, a constituent's letter supporting an agricultural price-support bill would appear under Subject Files. Agriculture. Drafts of that specific bill might be under Legislation. Material on an agricultural cooperative project in the Third District would be in the County Project Files. A constituent's request for exemption from certain federal regulations regarding crop measurement would be under Federal and State Agencies. Agriculture, Department of. For more information summarizing the contents of each category see the introductions at the beginning of each section in the inventory.
The papers reflect many types of public opinion: organized and repetitive pressure mail, professional lobbying activities of national interest groups, letters ranging from semi-literate constituents to well-known local and national leaders. The papers show a definite paper spiral during the 1960s and 1970s with the volume of Henderson's files increasing yearly.
The Henderson Papers illustrate many national trends of the 1960s and 1970s. Henderson's work on the Post Office and Civil Service and the Public Works committees made him instrumental in matters of national importance and brought him correspondence from around the nation. These papers particularly reveal trends in federal employment practices in the 1960s and 1970s. The papers contain much material about the reorganization of the Post Office Department into the Postal Service in 1969-1970. The papers reveal public opinion and legislative trends on such issues as civil rights, the Vietnamese War, the energy crisis of the early 1970s, and the Watergate affair. Henderson illustrates well the position of a conservative southern Democratic congressman voting against all civil rights legislation, opposing extension and raising of the minimum wage, federal aid to education, the War Against Poverty, and foreign aid. He consistently supported the presidents' positions on Vietnam, right-to-Work laws, and agricultural price supports.
The Henderson Papers contain rich information on local interests, affairs, and personalities in the Third District of North Carolina. Henderson vigorously supported local interests in Congress. He vehemently opposed restrictions on tobacco advertising and other anti-tobacco legislation. Henderson's correspondence and campaign material reveal the network of the Democratic political machinery in eastern North Carolina and his relationship with the local power structure.
Specific subjects are discussed in more detail in the inventory.
Civil rights -- United States -- Codification; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974; Federal aid to education; Civil service -- United States; Minimum wage -- Law and legislation -- United States; United States -- Foreign economic relations; Tobacco -- Law and legislation -- United States; Vietnamese Conflict, 1961-1975; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century; North Carolina -- Politics and government; Legislators -- United States -- Correspondence; Public welfare -- Law and legislation -- United States; Postal service -- Law and legislation -- United States; Henderson, David Newton, 1921-
- Campaign Files Series
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains correspondence, notes, and newspaper clippings concerning Henderson's congressional campaigns, 1960-1974. Henderson concentrated most of his time and attention to the Democratic primary in May of each election year. There is much less material about the November election. The Campaign Files contain many lists of electoral officials, party leaders, and targeted support groups, e.g. teachers, veterans. The papers reveal the rising importance of television in political campaigns of the mid to late 1960s.
  - 1960
    - Carteret County (Box 1)
    - Congratulations (Box 1)
    - Contributions (Box 1)
    - Craven County (Box 1)
    - Duplin County (Box 1)
    - Jones County (Box 1)
    - Lists (Box 1)
    - National Election (Box 1)
    - Onslow County (Box 1)
    - Pamlico County (Box 1)
    - Rallies (Box 1)
    - Speaking Engagements (Box 1)
    - Wayne County (Box 1)
    - Miscellany (Box 1)
  - 1962
    - Carteret County (Box 2)
    - Chalk, Skinner A. (Box 2)
    - Congratulations (Box 2)
    - Craven County (Box 2)
    - Duplin County (Box 2)
    - Election Returns (Box 2)
    - Harnett County (Box 2)
    - Jones County (Box 2)
    - Lists (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Publicity (Box 2)
    - Onslow County (Box 2)
    - Pamlico County (Box 2)
    - Pender County (Box 2)
    - Rallies (Box 2)
    - Sampson County (Box 2)
    - Simpkins, James O. (Box 2)
    - Wayne County (Box 2)
    - Miscellany (Box 2)
  - 1964
    - Election Returns (Box 3)
    - Lists (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Publicity (Box 3)
    - Rallies (Box 3)
    - Miscellany (Box 3)
  - 1965
    - Local Elections (Box 3)
  - 1966
    - Election Returns (Box 3)
    - Fall Schedule (Box 3)
    - Lee County (Box 3)
    - Lists (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Publicity (Box 3)
    - Newspaper Publicity. Don Howell (Box 3)
    - Rallies (Box 4)
    - Miscellany (Box 4)
  - 1968
    - Advertising. Newspaper Rates (Box 4)
    - Advertising. Radio Rates (Box 4)
    - Advertising. Television Rates (Box 4)
    - Congratulations (Box 4)
    - Election Returns (Box 4)
    - Lists (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Publicity (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Publicity. Herbert Howell (Box 4)
    - Newspaper Publicity. Paid Political Advertisements (Box 5)
    - Recording Studio (Box 5)
    - Wayne County (Box 5)
    - Miscellany (Box 5)
  - 1970
    - Carteret County (Box 6)
    - Cole, Jack (Box 6)
    - Congratulations (Box 6)
    - Contributions (Box 6)
    - Duplin County (Box 6)
    - Fund Raising (Box 6)
    - Godfrey, Horace. Campaign Fund (Box 7)
    - Harnett County (Box 7)
    - Howell Newsletters (Box 7)
    - Johnston County (Box 7)
    - Kornegay, Horace. Campaign Fund (Box 7)
    - Lists (Box 7)
    - Merchants (Box 7)
    - Onslow County (Box 7)
    - Pender County (Box 8)
    - Public Opinion Poll. Results (Box 8)
    - Sampson County (Box 8)
    - Wayne County (Box 8)
    - Miscellany (Box 8)
  - 1972
    - Advertising. Newspapers (Box 9)
    - Advertising. Radio (Box 9)
    - Candidates. Election Forms (Box 9)
    - Congratulations (Box 9)
    - Contributions (Box 9)
    - Election Returns (Box 9)
    - Lists (Box 9)
    - North Carolinians for Henderson Campaign Committee (Box 9)
    - Reception (Box 9)
    - Third District Convention (Box 9)
    - Miscellany (Box 9)
  - 1974
    - Congratulations (Box 9)
    - Miscellany (Box 9)
  - 1976
    - Miscellany (Box 9)
- Case Files Series
  The Case Files formed a massive part of Henderson's office files. They consist of correspondence from constituents and Henderson's responses concerning problems and requests of all sorts such as pensions, military transfers, job requests, etc. Since these papers are very routine and not topical in nature, a representative sample has been retained only for the letter C, a large letter which includes a wide range of ethnic groups.
  - Cable - Cain, Coleman (Box 10)
  - Cain, E. W. Jr. - Caison, John Allen (Box 10)
  - Caison, Jessie - Calhoun, Nelson (Box 10)
  - Callahan, R. P. - Cameron, Angus C. (Box 10)
  - Cameron, Carl S. - Cameron, Mayo (Box 10)
  - Camp Lejeune Motel - Campbell, Austin (Box 10)
  - Campbell, Betty - Campbell College: 1966 (Box 10)
  - Campbell College: 1967-1971 (Box 11)
  - Campbell College. ROTC - Campbell, Debra (Box 11)
  - Campbell, Gene - Canaday, Oliver L. (Box 11)
  - Canady, Annie Mae - Canady, William (Box 11)
  - Canfield, T. - Cannon, Lester Craig (Box 12)
  - Cannon, R. E. - Capps, Arthur (Box 12)
  - Capps, Daniel W. - Carawan, U. (Box 12)
  - Carawan, S/Sgt. Walt Jr. - Carlough, Richard (Box 12)
  - Carlton, Katie M. - Carobell Children's Home (Box 12)
  - Carolina Air Traders, Inc. - Carolina Power and Light (Box 12)
  - Carpenter, Aaron - Carr, Billy (Box 13)
  - Carr, Billy Wayne - Carr, John S. Jr. (Box 13)
  - Carr, Joseph R. - Carr, Susan (Box 13)
  - Carr, William H. - Carraway, Henry D. (Box 13)
  - Carraway, Thomas G. - Carroll, Helen (Box 13)
  - Carroll, Ina - Carter, A. Harvey (Box 13)
  - Carter, Carl - Carter, Charlotte Louise (Box 13)
  - Carter, Curtis - Carter, Isaac (Box 14)
  - Carter, Jeff K. - Carter, Molly (Box 14)
  - Carter, Norwood S. - Carter, William H. (Box 14)
  - Carter, W. Jeffrey - Carteret County News-Times (Box 14)
  - Carteret County Technical Institute - Carver, Steven (Box 14)
  - Casals, Thomas S. - Cash, Morris Jr. (Box 14)
  - Cashwell, Frank - Cassiano, Frank (Box 14)
  - Castel, Joseph L. Jr. - Catherine's Lake Community Association (Box 15)
  - Cato, Mrs. James - Caudell, Sylvia (Box 15)
  - Caudell, Virginia - Cavenaugh, Melbourne Q. (Box 15)
  - Cavenaugh, Norwood - Census. Eastern North Carolina (Box 15)
  - Central Carolina College - Chadwick, Bobby (Box 15)
  - Chadwick, Brenda - Chalk, William B. Jr. (Box 15)
  - Chalmers, James (Box 16)
  - Chamberlin, William L. - Chance, E. E. Jr. (Box 16)
  - Chandler, Dr. Lawrence V. - Chappell, James F. (Box 16)
  - Chappelle, Jesse M. - Cherry, Marvin W. (Box 16)
  - Cherry, Russell - Chestnut, Edwin Odell (Box 16)
  - Chestnut, Felix W.- Christy, Julia (Box 16)
  - Church, Freddy Joe - Civils, Ronald (Box 17)
  - Clark, Andrew B. - Clark, James L. (Box 17)
  - Clark, James W. - Clark, John T. (Box 17)
  - Clark, Kirby C. - Clayton, Robert C. (Box 17)
  - Cleal, Carol - Cloud, Roddie M. (Box 17)
  - Coursey, Raymond - Coats, William J. (Box 17)
  - Cobb, Dennis R. - Coffman, Karen (Box 17)
  - Cogan, Harry J. - Cold Storage Plant. Morehead City (Box 18)
  - Cole, Carrol H. - Coleman, Hurtis (Box 18)
  - Coleman, Larry - Coley, David H. (Box 18)
  - Coley, D. M. Sr. - Collier, Joe (Box 18)
  - Collier, Lynwood R. - Collins, Helen (Box 18)
  - Collins, Kenneth - Combs, Gene (Box 18)
  - Combs, Tommy - Conner, Charles W. (Box 18)
  - Conner, Donald C. Jr. - Cook, Anna J. (Box 19)
  - Cook, Clyde R. - Cook, James H. (Box 19)
  - Cook, Jerry - Cook, Sam (Box 19)
  - Cooke, Bobby Earle - Coombs, McIver (Box 19)
  - Cooney, Dan - Cooper, Theodora (Box 19)
  - Cooper, Thomas - Corbin, Nadine (Box 19)
  - Cordell, Charlie - Cording, Melvin (Box 19)
  - Cordova, Paul - Cortez, Jimmy Jr. (Box 20)
  - Costlow, Dr. John D. - Cottle, Charles (Box 20)
  - Cottle, Haywood W. - Couch, Early W. (Box 20)
  - Couch, George W. - Covan, Harvey (Box 20)
  - Courman, Jessie Mae - Cowgill, E. W. (Box 20)
  - Cowgill, James - Cox, Mrs. Duncan L. (Box 20)
  - Cox, Edith - Cox, Jesse (Box 20)
  - Cox, J. R. - Cox, Robert (Box 20)
  - Cox, Sadie - Craver, Paul (Box 21)
  - Crawford, E. Gordon - Crawford, William H. (Box 21)
  - Craven, James B. III - Creech, David (Box 21)
  - Creech, Frank - Creech, Lones Wayne (Box 21)
  - Creech, Mrs. Mabel - Cron, Eugene (Box 21)
  - Croom, Elizabeth A. - Crowe, Jim (Box 21)
  - Crowe, John - Crumpler, Joseph H. (Box 21)
  - Crumpler, Thomas M. - Cruse, Ottis (Box 22)
  - Cuddington, Frank - Cullingford, William B. (Box 22)
  - Cummings, Billy Ray - Curtis, Mrs. Howard (Box 22)
  - Curtis, James - Cyr, Kathleen (Box 22)
- Committee Files Series
  Concerns Henderson's work on the Post Office and Civil Service and Public Works committees and their various subcommittees. Contains correspondence from constituents relating to issues before the committees and much national correspondence from lobbyists and concerned parties. This category also contains much printed material, reports of committee hearings, and notes and documents relating to the formation of specific bills. Committee Files were arranged by committee, subcommittee, then general subjects within the committee.
  - POST OFFICE AND CIVIL SERVICE COMMITTEE
    - Post Office and Civil Service, 1961-1976 (Box 23-37)
      Contains miscellaneous material about committee matters.
    - Subcommittee Files
      - Census and Government Statistics, Subcommittee on, 1961-1964 (Box 38)
      - Census and Population, Subcommittee on, 1975-1976 (Box 38)
      - Employee Political Rights and Intergovernmental Program, Subcommittee on, 1975-1976 (Box 38)
      - Investigations, Subcommittee on, 1973 (Box 38)
    - Manpower Utilization Subcommittee
      Henderson became chairman of this subcommittee in 1963. Committee name was changed in 1967. See below.
      - Manpower Utilization, Subcommittee on, 1961-1963 (Box 39)
      - Manpower Utilization, Subcommittee on, 1964-1966 (Box 40)
      - Civil Service Commission, 1962-1964 (Box 40)
      - Discriminatory Hiring Practices, 1963 (Box 40)
      - Executive Session, 1964 (Box 40)
      - Hearings on Office of Economic Opportunity, 1965 (Box 40)
      - Little Rock Case, 1963 (Box 40)
      - Special, 1965-1966 (Box 40)
      - Wright-Patterson Air Force Base, Ohio, 1963 (Box 40)
    - Manpower and Civil Service Subcommittee
      - Manpower and Civil Service, 1967-1976 (Box 41-44)
      - Army Material Command Reduction in Forces, 1970 (Box 45)
      - Referrals, 1966-1970 (Box 45)
      - Selective Service System, 1969-1972 (Box 45)
    - Postal Facilities and Mail, Subcommittee on, 1972-1976 (Box 46)
    - Postal Operations, Subcommittee on, 1965 (Box 46)
    - Postal Service Subcommittee
      - Postal Service Subcommittee, 1973-1976 (Box 46)
      - Hearing, 1973 (Box 46)
    - Retirement and Employee Benefits Subcommittee, 1973-1976 (Box 47)
    - Retirement, Insurance, and Health Benefits Subcommittee, 1970 (Box 48)
    - Non-Subcommittee Files
      - Citizens' Committee for Postal Reform, Inc., 1969 (Box 48)
      - Citrus Shipping, 1974 (Box 48)
      - Civil Service Commission Briefing, 1971-1972 (Box 48)
      - Committee Organization, 1966-1967 (Box 48)
      - Committee Organization, 1968-1973 (Box 49)
      - Committee Staffs, 1971 (Box 49)
      - Executive Pay Levels, 1973 (Box 49)
      - Executive Pay Raise, 1975 (Box 49)
      - Guam Wage Board Employees, 1971-1972 (Box 50)
      - Labor-Management Relations, 1969 (Box 50)
      - Mailing Practices of Executive Agencies, 1969-1974 (Box 50)
      - Murphy, Richard. Testimony on Pay Bills, 1967 (Box 50)
      - Obscenity in the Mails, 1971 (Box 51)
      - Parcel Post Revision, 1966 (Box 51)
      - Patronage, 1973-1974 (Box 52)
      - Photographs, 1974 (Box 52)
      - Postal Pay, 1970 (Box 52)
      - Postal Rates, 1967, 1970-1974 (Box 52)
      - Postal Rates, 1975 (Box 53)
      - Postal Reform
        In 1969 through 1970 the Post Office Department experienced a major reorganization. First introduced in 1969 as H.R. 4, this reform was finally implemented in 1970 as H.R. 17070. This legislation converted the Post Office Department from a Cabinet-level department to an independent establishment in the executive branch of government. This independence necessitated reorganizing rates so that revenues of the Postal Service as a whole met expenses. The bills provided the framework for collective bargaining by postal employees, and enhanced the pay scale and advancement opportunities. One oversized item is located in oversized box at end of collection.
        - Postal Reform, 1969 (Box 53)
        - Postal Reform, 1970 (Box 54)
        - Air Transportation Amendment, 1969 (Box 55)
        - Conference, July, 1970 (Box 55)
        - Correspondence, 1970, January-June (Box 55)
        - Correspondence, 1970, July-December (Box 56)
        - Finance Commission Amendment, 1969 (Box 56)
        - Henderson Amendment, 1970.Proposed amendment to allow the employee the right to join or not to join a labor organization. (Box 56)
        - Henderson Amendment. Thank you Notes, 1970 (Box 56)